KRZYSZTOF S. STOPKA

Connect with me on LinkedIn stopka.kris@gmail.com (773) 580 – 7206 Google Scholar

<u>GOAL</u>: To work as a post-doctoral researcher, expand my knowledge base while contributing to cutting edge computational materials science research coupled with experiments and data science, and then to eventually obtain a tenure track academic faculty position or national laboratory research scientist position.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

David L. McDowell Group, Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA

Aug 2016 - May 2021

"ICME Workflows for Rapid Exploration of Process-Structure-Property Relations of Fatigue-Critical Metallic Components"

- Performing large-scale Crystal Plasticity finite element simulations of duplex Ti-6Al-4V and Al7075-T6
- Implementing Python-scripted workflows to explore extreme value fatigue response of intrinsic (grain size, shape, and orientation distributions) and extrinsic (residual stress, surface roughness, inclusions, or pores, etc.) microstructure attributes under various loading and boundary conditions
- Developing novel methods to simulation-based, microstructure-sensitive multiaxial fatigue
- Contributing to ONR Agile ICME program via collaborations on open-source PRISMS-Plasticity platform at University of Michigan

X-ray Science Division, Argonne National Laboratory, Lemont, IL Graduate Researcher

May – September 2020

- Analyzed high-energy x-ray diffraction data collected in situ during fatigue testing of Ti-6Al-4V
- Reconstructed digital microstructure for crystal plasticity simulations using data fusion approaches

EDUCATION

Doctor of Philosophy, Mechanical Engineering Georgia Institute of Technology, *Atlanta, GA*

May 2021

Master of Science, Mechanical Engineering

May 2018

Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA

Bachelor of Science, Mechanical Engineering

Nov 2015

Minor in Computational Science

Rose-Hulman Institute of Technology, Terre Haute, IN

PUBLICATIONS

- M. Yaghoobi, K. S. Stopka, A. Lakshmanan, V. Sundararaghavan, J. E. Allison, and D. L. McDowell, "PRISMS-Fatigue computational framework for fatigue analysis in polycrystalline metals and alloys," npj Computational Materials 7 (2021) 38, doi
- K. S. Stopka and D. L. McDowell, "Microstructure-Sensitive Computational Multiaxial Fatigue of Al 7075-T6 and Duplex Ti-6Al-4V," *International Journal of Fatigue*, 133 (2020) 105460, doi
- K. S. Stopka and D. L. McDowell, "Microstructure-Sensitive Computational Estimates of Driving Forces for Surface Versus Subsurface Fatigue Crack Formation in Duplex Ti-6Al-4V and Al 7075-T6," JOM, 72 (2020) 28, doi
- K. S. Stopka, T. Gu, and D. L. McDowell, "Effects of algorithmic simulation parameters on the prediction of extreme value fatigue indicator parameters in duplex Ti-6Al-4V," *International Journal of Fatigue*, 141 (2020) 105865, doi
- T. Gu, **K. S. Stopka**, C. Xu, and D. L. McDowell, "Prediction of Maximum Fatigue Indicator Parameters for Duplex Ti-6Al-4V using Extreme Value Theory," *Acta Materialia*, 188 (2020) 504-516, doi
- A. E. Tallman, K. S. Stopka, L. P. Swiler, Y. Wang, S. R. Kalidindi, and D. L. McDowell, "Gaussian-Process-Driven Adaptive Sampling for Reduced-Order Modeling of Texture Effects in Polycrystalline Alpha-Ti," JOM, 71 (2019) 2646, doi
- K. S. Stopka, G. Whelan, and D. L. McDowell, "Microstructure-Sensitive ICME Workflows for Fatigue Critical Applications," Society of the Advancement of Material and Process Engineering (SAMPE) Conference Proceedings (2019), doi

PRESENTATIONS

- K. S. Stopka and D. L. McDowell, "Effects of surface roughness on microstructure-sensitive computations of fatigue crack formation driving force in duplex Ti-6Al-4V and Al 7075-T6," The Minerals, Metals & Materials Society (TMS) 2020, San Diego, CA, February 26th, 2020.
- K. S. Stopka and D. L. McDowell, "Microstructure-Sensitive Computational Estimates of Driving Forces for Surface vs. Subsurface Fatigue Crack Formation in Duplex Ti-6Al-4V and Al 7075-T6," Materials Science and Technology (MS&T) 2019, Portland, OR, September 30th, 2019.
- K. S. Stopka and D. L. McDowell, "Microstructure-Sensitive Computational Multiaxial Fatigue," 12th International Conference on Multiaxial Fatigue and Fracture (ICMFF12) 2019, Bordeaux, France, June 24th, 2019.
- A. E. Tallman, K. S. Stopka, L. P. Swiler, Y. Wang, S. R. Kalidindi, and D. L. McDowell, "Gaussian-Process-Driven Adaptive Sampling for Reduced-Order Modeling of Texture Effects in Polycrystalline Alpha-Ti," The Minerals, Metals & Materials Society (TMS) 2019, San Antonio, TX, March 12th, 2019.
- **K. S. Stopka** and D. L. McDowell, "Computational Statistics of Formation and Early Growth of Microstructurally Small Cracks in Ti-6Al-4V," MS&T 2018, Columbus, OH, October 17th, 2018.

IN PREPARATION

- K. S. Stopka, M. Yaghoobi, J. E. Allison, and D. L. McDowell, "Modeling surface roughness in microstructure-sensitive computations of Al 7075-T6."
- K. S. Stopka, M. Yaghoobi, J. E. Allison, and D. L. McDowell, "Effects of boundary conditions on microstructure-sensitive fatigue crystal plasticity analysis."
- K. S. Stopka, M. Yaghoobi, J. E. Allison, and D. L. McDowell, "Microstructure effects on the extreme value fatigue response of FCC metals and alloys: Effects of sample size and grain neighborhood."

PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

• **Tech to Teaching,** Georgia Tech, Center for Teaching and Learning Fall 2019 – Fall 2020 Completed two graduate-level courses and a capstone teaching experience to prepare future faculty

EDITORIAL EXPERIENCE

Peer Reviewer for the following journals, <u>Publons Profile</u>

Mar 2019 – Present

- International Journal of Fatigue (IJF), 21 reviews
- Journal of The Minerals, Metals & Materials Society (TMS) (JOM), 2 reviews

INDUSTRY EXPERIENCE

B/E Aerospace, Rockford, IL

Dec 2015 - Jul 2016

Project Engineer

- Conducted Root Cause Analysis to improve reliability of Vacuum Pump
- Worked with customers / suppliers to improve Vacuum Pump performance for multiple aircraft
- Collaborated with design engineers to redesign Embraer Vacuum Waste System

GE Aviation, Evendale, OH

Jun - Aug 2015

GEnx Engine Performance Intern

- Remedied process of deriving humidity and condensation fan speed adders for production
- Calculated Test Vectors to support new 76K thrust rating for Boeing
- Determined effects of engine's physical turbine deviation on thrust and SFC

Space Exploration Technologies (SpaceX), Hawthorne, CA

Sep - Nov 2014

Structures Intern

- Designed testing fixture for v2.0 Landing Leg weather seal Research and Development
- Directed tensile, fatigue, torch, and vacuum testing to validate Pyron and Nomex felts as replacement for cork as Temperature Protection System on Falcon 9 Landing Legs
- Evaluated strength of Carbon Fiber samples with Composi-lok fasteners for v2.0 Landing Legs

GE Aviation, Rockford, IL Jun – Aug 2014

Manufacturing Engineering Intern

- Appraised LEAP combustor Nacelle Anti-Ice Valve drawings for manufacturability and cost
- Enhanced Qualification Matrix to expand site worker versatility
- Created drawings and process plans for developmental parts using SolidWorks

Tesla Motors, Fremont, CA

Sep 2013 - Feb 2014

Craftsmanship Vehicle Engineering Intern

- Determined root cause and solution to Model S Instrument Panel fitment inconsistency
- Enriched Research and Development for Model X program to study what competitor vehicles are doing and set competitive or class leading margins for interior and exterior components
- Sourced an E-Cube and Blue Buck project to aid Model X future dimensional quality
- Lead and assisted in custom Model S builds to assess new and modified components

GE Aviation, Terre Haute, IN

Mar – Aug 2013

Manufacturing Engineering Intern

- Completed weld certifications and gathered dimensional data for Passport and LEAP combustors
- Interpreted GD&T blueprints for online characteristic accountability system
- Updated operation sketches, part routers and check sheets

Diesel Radiator Company, Melrose Park, IL

Jun - Aug 2012

Design and Manufacturing Engineering Intern

- Reduced steel scrap by an average of 9.7% for high quantity radiator jobs
- Designed facility apparatuses, such as stainless-steel ductwork, and a brass uncoiler and shear rail
- Resolved day to day computer numerical control issues affecting production

LEADERSHIP

Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA

Aug 2018 - May 2019

Leadership Education and Development (LEAD) Coach

- Met one-on-one with undergraduate and graduate students for personalized coaching sessions
- Developed a total of six students during the 2018-2019 academic year

Pi Kappa Alpha Fraternity, $Terre\ Haute,\ IN$

Mar - Nov 2015

Scholarship Chairman

- Rewarded academic excellence through monetary awards, dinners, and chapter recognition
- Supported collaboration between brothers in current and future classes
- Maintained database of collective study material and study room supplies
- Established weekly study hall sessions to provide additional assistance to brothers
- Educated freshman struggling with MatLab programing course

AWARDS

- President's Fellowship Georgia Institute of Technology (2016-2020)
- Graduate Scholarship Polish National Alliance (2016 2019)
- Undergraduate Scholarship Polish National Alliance (2011 2015)
- Scholar of the year Pi Kappa Alpha Fraternity (2015)

SKILLS

- Background: Mechanics of materials, applied mechanics, computational materials science, fatigue and fracture, numerical analysis and modeling, data science
- Languages: Python, MatLab, FORTRAN, C++, Polish, Spanish
- Software: ABAQUS, ANSYS, SolidWorks, NX, DREAM.3D, WinSCP, Git, ParaView
- Hobbies: Fitness, running, hiking, mentorship